Md Khalid Athar

Java Full stack Developer | Ph: 8436231430 | Email: khalidathar96@gmail.com | Hyderabad

Declaration of Intent:

Skilled Java developer with 3 years of experience building enterprise applications using technologies like Java, Spring Boot, Hibernate JPA, microservices, Rest API, Kafka and MySQL. Possess ability to design, develop, and deploy complex software from scratch. Self-motivated software developer with problem solving skills who can work effectively as part of a team or independently.

Professional Outline:

- IT specialist with around 3 years' experience as a backend Java developer
- Using Java 8, Spring MVC, and Spring Boot to create scalable microservices through design and development.
- Integrated **Kafka** for real-time data processing and event-driven communication, which improves system responsiveness.
- Implemented Eureka for service discovery, which allowed load balancing and seamless interaction across microservices.
- Enhanced system fault tolerance and resilience in a Supply chain context by implementing **Resilience4**j.
- Collaborated with cross-functional teams to use **MySQL** and **Hibernate JPA** to develop and improve database schemas.
- Built industry-standard **RESTful APIs** to facilitate seamless interaction with third-party Marketing systems.
- Employed caching approaches using **Redis** to reduce latency and enhance application performance.
- Implemented **multithreading** techniques to maximize parallel processing and improve overall system performance.
- Utilized **Mockito** and **JUnit** to conduct comprehensive unit tests, assuring the precision and dependability of the codebase.
- Integrating CI/CD pipelines to automate the build, test, and deployment processes.
- Integrated Spring Actuator to oversee and control the supply chain and telecom application's health.

Technical Expertise:

- **Programming Languages:** Java/Java 8, Python
- Frameworks: Spring boot, Spring MVC, ReactJs
- Microservices Architecture: Design and implementation, Eureka
- APIs: Restful API, API Gateway
- Message Brokers: Kafka
- Message Brokers Kark
- **Testing:** Junit, Postman
- Resilience: Resilience4j
- Web Technologies: Json, Rest-Template, Web-client, Rest-Client
- Databases: MySQL, PostgreSQL, Hibernate/JPA
- Development Tools: IntelliJ IDEA, Git/GitHub
- Methodologies: Agile/Scrum

Professional Experience:

Techprojects India private Limited, Hyderabad | Java Developer | December 2022 - Present

Project: CSWG Vendor Portal (Supply chain Project)

Description: Vendor Portal Revolutionizing vendor management with streamlined onboarding, catalogue management, and real-time order tracking. Robust inventory tools ensure seamless interaction, fostering better collaboration.

Tools & Technology: Java, Spring boot, Microservice, Hibernate JPA, Kafka, Rest Api, Junit, Docker, Kubernetes, MySQL, AWS.

Role & Responsibilities:

- Developing test-driven applications using Java, Spring Boot, Hibernate JPA and microservice architecture for a grocery-based client with 10,000+ vendors and 7,500+ stores.
- An adaptable and responsive system is ensured by employing **Eureka** for smooth load balancing and service discovery, and by implementing **Kafka** into practice for event-driven communication.
- Robust functionality and effortless integration are made possible by promoting system resilience and fault tolerance with Resilience4j, collaborating on database schema design with Hibernate JPA and MySQL, and following industry standards for building RESTful APIs.
- Utilize Kafka to improve system responsiveness and event-driven communication.
- Utilize Eureka for service discovery, enabling seamless communication and load balancing.
- To improve fault tolerance and system resilience, **Resilience4j** was implemented.
- Utilized **Hibernate JPA** and **MySQL** in conjunction with teams to create and optimize database schemas.
- For seamless integration, **RESTful APIs** were developed in accordance with industry norms.
- Utilized **Redis** to implement caching techniques, which enhanced application speed.
- Used **Mockito** and **JUnit** to do unit tests.
- Integrated **Spring Actuator** for controlling and observing the Supply chain application's health.
- Integrating CI/CD pipelines to automate the build, test, and deployment processes

Tata Consultancy Services, Bengaluru | Java Developer | November 2018 - February 2020

Project: DT TelecomSphere (Telecom Project)

Description: DT TelecomSphere enables digital service providers (DSP) and their telecom partners to collaborate cooperatively to handle each phase of the process in a transparent manner, including partner onboarding to billing and resolution of disputes.

Tools & Technology: Java, Spring boot, Microservice, Hibernate JPA, Kafka, Rest Api, Junit, PostgreSQL, Linux

Client: Deutsche Telekom | Process: Agile | Domain: Telecommunication | Duration -1+ year

Role & Responsibilities:

- Developed secure and compliant software solutions for the Telecom client, utilizing **Java, Spring Boot** and **Hibernate JPA** impacting more than 250 million users .
- Collaborated with cross-functional teams to design and implement scalable telecom applications, incorporating microservices architecture and Eureka for service registration and discovery.
- Conducted API testing using **Postman**, ensuring adherence to specifications.
- Utilized **Resilience4j** to implement resilience patterns and enhance system stability, ensuring graceful handling of failures. Worked on feature development, bug fixing, and system optimization.
- Implement Hibernate JPA with PostgreSQL for seamless database operations, ensuring data consistency.
- Implement multithreading techniques to optimize parallel processing and system efficiency.
- Collaborate with front-end developers to integrate backend services, ensuring end-to-end functionality.
- Implement security measures in API Gateway for managing and securing API endpoints.
- Utilize Spring Actuator for monitoring and managing the health of the telecom application.
- Integrate **RESTful APIs** for communication between telecom application modules.

Educational Qualification:

- Masters of degree (Computer Application) from 2020-2022.
- Bachelors of degree (Computer Application) from 2015-2018.

Declaration

I hereby confirm that the information above is accurate to the greatest extent of my knowledge and accept responsibility for its correctness.

Md Khalid Athar